Let's look inside the copper wire.
Battery, wire and switch: our circuit is ready.
We are magnifying a tiny part of the wire.
Blue dots represent electrons already in the copper.
The switch is open: there is no overall flow.
Copper ions vibrate; mobile electrons move randomly.
Switch closed: electrons begin to drift.
The battery provides an electrical push through the wire.
Follow the electrons: in from the left, out to the right.
From the negative terminal (-) towards the positive (+).
Current is flowing. Now let's reveal its magnetic field.
Three green circles show the field around this wire.
Let's slowly return to the whole circuit.
The current and its magnetic field continue.
The wire is part of one complete circuit.
The field guides are enlarged to keep them visible.
Electron flow and conventional current are opposite.
Electrons: - to +. Conventional current: + to -.
Open the switch: the current and its field stop.
Next: what could make the magnetic field stronger?